Preliminary Inventory to the Briegleb Collection, 1938-1949
Hoover Institution Archives
Briegleb Collection,
1938-1949
XX049
Briegleb, collector.
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Letters, reports, and memoranda, relating to the political and economic situation in Germany and in Eastern Europe, primarily from 1945-1949, the Nuremberg war crime trials, and communism in Germany after World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
Communism.; Communism--Germany.; Nuremberg Trial of Major German War Criminals, 1945-1946.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Germany.; War crime trials.; World War, 1939-1945.; Europe, Eastern.; Germany.; Germany--History--1945-1955
Container List
- 1. Kulturbund Berlin. Its organization. Activities of several members (Box 1.)
- 2. (continued). Report of activities of further persons
- 3. Hausobleute (House Police) in the Eastern Zone. The SED party surveillance
- 4. Use of German scholars for European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan)
- 5. "Denazification: Remarks on the Law" from the Swiss newspaper Die Tat, 1946
- 6. The Nuremberg Trial. Letter of U.S. Attorney Carroll to General Lucius D. Clay
- 7. "Berlin and Its Effects in the West" from an article in Zurich's Weltwoche, 1948 April 7
- 8. Present attitudes in Germany. Remarks of former SS leader
- 9. "The SS State" by Eugen Kogon. Criticism of the book
- 10. War prisoners and workers from the East during the Second World War
- 11. The Nuremberg Trial. Report of K. I. Albrecht
- 12. KPD, Germany. Report of meeting of the KPD, SPD, KAPD in Ulm, 1948 February 1
- 13. Peoples in the East. Memorandum on Rosenberg's attitude toward them
- 14. The Nuremberg Trial. Report of witness of process "Wilhelmstrasse"
- 15. Western Powers - Russia. Remarks on impossibility of understanding between them
- 16. Battle against Bolshevism. Remarks on formation of group as bulwark against it
- 17. Letter of K. I. Albrecht, author of "The Betrayed Socialism" to Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller, 1948
- 18. Excerpt from a letter of Fieldmarshall Manstein, prisoner in England, 1947
- 19. a. Yugoslav rebellion against the Kremlin b. Addition to above
- 19. b. Addition to above
- 20. Request for investigation of conditions in SS prisoner-of-war camp, Lambach
- 21. Protocol on interrogation of witness K. I. Albrecht by Dr. Fröschmann
- 22. German POWs in Yugoslavia. Report from Yugoslavia
- 23. The last words of Professor Karl Brand under the gallows, 1948 June 2
- 24. Reichssicherheitshauptamt, SS Oberabschnitt Süd-West: Directives on measures against the Catholic Church, 1938 February 15
- 25. Report on the Nuremberg Trial from the periodical Christ und Welt
- 26a. Regarding Malmedy process. Mistreatment of German POWs by Americans
- 26b. Sworn statement of above
- 27. Hitler and Eva Braun
- 28. Hitler's knowledge and intellectual faculties
- 29. Chain letter sent to thousands of former German officers and men
- 30. K. I. Albrecht's statement on "How Must We Fight Bolshevism?"
- 31. K. I. Albrecht's view on Bolshevik victory in China, the result of long-range planning
- 32. Von Krosigk's (?) report on Hitler's policy
- 33. General Jodl's opinions about the U.S. - Soviet war, 1946 August
- 34. Rudolf Lehmann, judge, accused at Nuremberg. Statement to his friends, 1948 November 15
- 35. Von Hasselbach: "Dr. Morell, Hitler's Physician"
- 36. The national-socialist revolution of the lower middle class (anonymous)
- 37. Statement by Manstein, Brauchitsch, Halder prepared for the Nuremberg Trial, not submitted
- 38. Article by an officer on the inside story of the Supreme Command, and Hitler's role therein
- 39. Observations and remarks on German General Staff
- 40. Thoughts on collaboration (at present time
- 41. K. I. Albrecht, "The Decisive Factor"
- 42. Arno Schreiber's report on his experience as POW of the French
- 43. Interrogation of former Gauleiter (Baden, Alsace) Wagner and former Fieldmarshall Keitel
- 44. Hans Raupach: Socialization of industries in satellite states and its economic-political significance
- 45. Report on organization of indoctrination of the SED (Eastern Zone)
- 46. Speech of Walter Ulbricht, 1948 August 27 (never published)
- 47. "Marshall Plan 1948 - Without Illusions" (in English)
- 48. K. I. Albrecht, "Vyshinsky: Hangman of the Old Guard of Lenin," 1949 March 10
- 49. Translation from periodical Hungaria (published in Munich, 1949, No 1)
- 50. Bolshevik gains all over the world. Results of planning
- 51. K. I. Albrecht: Exploring and combating Bolshevism, 1949 February 16 1949 February 16
- 52. "Before the Storm," critical article on policy of Western Powers, by a member of the Reichstag in the Weimar period
- 53. Statistical data of CP in Austria (14th Congress)
- 54. Purges within the SED, by leading Berlin politician and economist
- 55. Roland Eck, "Our Fifth Column," in Rheinischer Merkur, 1949 February 1
- 56. "Limits of the Defensive," by member of the Reichstag in the Weimar period
- 57. Memorandum of German Volksrat, with additional remarks by Walter Ulbricht. See also Nos. 58 and 59
- 58. Basic outline for CP in its political work in Germany
- 59. Tasks of the party control commission of the SED
- 60. Hans Raupach: Soviet Rule and the Psychology of Southeastern Europe
- 61. "Will Southeastern Europe become Bolshevik?" Views of a political scientist
- 62. P. H. Seraphim and W. Conze: Poland's expansion toward the West: the question of Poland's Western frontier
- 63. Declaration of the KPD central committee on the political situation (pamphlet)
- 64. Directives of the KPD for organization and conduct in the struggle for unity and peace, 1949 March 5-6
- 65. The work of the KPD in the Ruhr
- 66. Resolution of the Central Committee of the KPD on youth policy, 1949 March 2
- 67. Tasks of the party control commission of the SED. Extract from directives issued by a Kreisverband
- 68. Silesia, the country of the most complete self-sufficiency
- 69. Gottlob Berger, former SS General: letter to his friends, 1949 April 30
- 70. The extinction of the Germans at Werschetz
- 71. German Politics Today?
- 72. The situation (1949 May)
- 73. Political motivating forces and national-political developments in the Eastern Zone
- 74. "Democracy and the Civil War," by a member of the Reichstag of the Weimar period
- 75. "Europe's Latest Zone of Unrest: The Slavic Wall and Its Cracks"
- 76. Report on the agricultural situation in the former territory of Silesia
- 77. "Cultural Bolshevism and National Bolshevism"
- 78. Political Indoctrination and Training of the Police in the Eastern Zone
- 79. Members of the police in the Eastern Zone to join the international brigade in Greece
- 80. The organization of indoctrination of the SED in Thuringia
- 81. Letter of an uneasy German and Pieck's (chairman of the SED) answer. Communist propaganda pamphlet